Curriculum Vitae

KC Sivaramakrishnan

Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge

August 19, 2016

15 JJ Thomson Avenue Cambridge CB3 0FD Tel: +44 79828 42499

Aug 2011 – Dec 2011

Summary

I am interested in the design and implementation of concurrent programming languages targeting scalable platforms such as many-core processors and compute clouds. My research spans programming models, compilers, static analysis, schedulers, threading systems, and memory management.

Education

PhD — Computer Science May 2011 - Dec 2014 Purdue University, USA Thesis Title: Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems

Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

Master of Science — Computer Science *Aug 2008 – May 2011* Purdue University, USA

GPA: 3.94/4 Bachelor of Engineering — Computer Science and Engineering Aug 2004 - May 2008

PSG College of Technology GPA: 9.55/10 Anna University, India

Experience

Research Associate, University of Cambridge

Dec 2014 - present Advisor: Anil Madhavapeddy Cambridge, UK

Developing Multicore OCaml under the OCaml Labs initiative in the Computer Laboratory.

Research Assistant, Purdue University

Aug 2008 - Dec 2014 Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan West Lafayette, IN, USA

My research focused on discovering new language abstractions and developing runtime system techniques to ease programming weakly consistent systems. To this end, I have built MultiMLton, a parallel and distributed extension of MLton Standard ML compiler and runtime and Quelea, a shallow extension of Haskell for declarative programming over eventually consistent data stores.

Teaching Assistant, Purdue University West Lafayette, IN, USA Undergraduate C Programming (CS180) Aug 2012 - Dec 2012

Graduate Programming Languages (CS565)

My tasks included designing and evaluating weekly projects, office hours for one-on-one instruction, and grading.

Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge Feb 2012 - May 2012 Advisors: Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, and Simon Peyton Jones Cambridge, UK

I developed a concurrency substrate for Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) to allow programmers to modularly implement user-level schedulers and concurrency libraries for Haskell threads in Haskell, without having to re-engineer critical runtime system components. The concurrency substrate is built around one-shot continuations and uses transactional memory for coordination.

Research Intern, Samsung Information Systems America (R&D) May 2010 - Aug 2010

Advisor: Daniel Waddington San Jose, CA, USA

I was part of the core team that developed SNAPPLE programming language - a safe and concurrent extension of C++ targeted at many-core processors. The task involved designing language extensions for concurrency, compiler extensions for safety, and a runtime for executing large number of lightweight threads. SNAPPLE was implemented as a veneer on top of C++ using LLNL Rose source-to-source compiler.

Intern, Advanced Numerical Research and Analysis Group

Dec 2007 - Apr 2008 Advisor: Sankar Chnab Hyderabad, India

As a part of the Compiler Engineering group, I ported Kaffe, an open source Java VM to an embedded microprocessor ANUPAMA and a desktop processor ABACUS. Developed a lightweight threading subsystem, and implemented a JIT backed for ABACUS.

Journal Publications

Composable Scheduler Activations for Haskell Jun 2016 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, Simon Peyton Jones J2 Journal of Functional Programming (JFP) Representation without Taxation: A Uniform, Low-Overhead, and High-Level Interface to Eventu-Mar 2016 ally Consistent Key-Value Stores J1 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan IEEE Data Engineering Bulletin, 39(1): 52 64, March 2016 MultiMLton: A Multicore-aware Runtime for Standard ML Nov 2014 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan J0 Journal of Functional Programming (JFP), 24(6): 613 - 674 **Efficient Sessions** Feb 2013 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Mohammad Qudeisat, Lukasz Ziarek, Karthik Nagaraj, Patrick Eugster J-1 Science of Computer Programming (SCP), 78(2): 147 - 167 Invited paper Conference Publications **Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores** Jun 2015 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan C7 International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) **Rx-CML:** A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony Jan 2014 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan C6 Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL) A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC Nov 2012 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan C5 Many-core Architecture Research Community Symposium (MARC) Best paper award **Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness** Jun 2012 C4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan International Symposium on Memory Management (ISMM) **Composable Asynchronous Events** Jun 2011 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan C3

C1

International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)

Efficient Session Type Guided Distributed Interaction

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Karthik Nagaraj, Lukasz Ziarek, Patrick Eugster

International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)

International Conference on Coordination Models and Languages (COORDINATION)

Partial Memoization of Concurrency and Communication Sep 2009 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan

June 2010

Workshop Publications

C2

W4	Lock-free programming for the masses KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tho Laurent OCaml Workshop	Sep 2016	
W3	Compiling Links Effect Handlers to the OCaml Backend Daniel Hillestrm, Sam Lindley, KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Worshop	Sep 2016	
W2	Eff Directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Workshop	Sep 2016	
W1	Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects Stephen Dolan, Leo White, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Jeremy Yallop and Anil Madhavapeddy OCaml Workshop	Sep 2015	
W0	Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2013	
W-1	Scalable Lightweight Task Management Schemes for MIMD Processors Daniel G. Waddington, Chen Tian, KC Sivaramakrishnan Workshop on Systems for Future Multi-Core Architectures (SFMA)	Apr 2011	
W-2	The Design Rationale for MultiMLton Suresh Jagannathan, Armand Navabi, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek ML Workshop	Sep 2010	
W-3	Lightweight Asynchrony using Parasitic Threads KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Raghavendra Prasad, Suresh Jagannathan Workshop on Declarative Aspects of Multicore Programming (DAMP)	Jan 2010	
❖ Technical Reports and Drafts			
T2	Featherweight Threads for Communication KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Purdue University Computer Science Technical Report – TR-11-018	Nov 2011	

Teaching/Advising

- Guest Lectures:
 - Arrows, Advanced Functional Programming, University of Cambridge, Lent 2015–16.
 - Debugging, Programming in C and C++, University of Cambridge, Michelmas 2015–16.
- Supervisions at University of Cambridge:
 - Algorithms, Lent 2015–16.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent 2015–16.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Michaelmas 2015–16.
 - Object-oriented Programming, Michaelmas 2015–16.
- Teaching assistantships at Purdue University
 - Undergraduate C Programming (CS180), Aug 2012 Dec 2012.
 - Graduate Programming Languages (CS565), Aug 2011 Dec 2011.
- Projects supervised:

- James Wright, University of Cambridge, Mechanized semantics of Algebraic Effects in OCaml, Michelmas 2015 present.
- Armael Gueneau, ENS de Lyon, Algebraic Effects for js_of_ocaml, Sep 2015 present.
- Theo Laurent, ENS de Lyon, Reagents for Multicore OCaml, May 2015 Aug 2015.
- Guillain Potron, ENS de Lyon, Semantics of Irmin branch-consistent data store, March 2015 Aug 2015.

Talks

14110	
OCaml Platform: Update OCaml Consortium Meeting	Nov 2015 Paris, France
Multicore OCaml: Update OCaml Developer's Meeting	Nov 2015 Paris, France
Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects OCaml Workshop 2015	Sep 2015 Vancouver, Canada
Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems PhD Defense	Dec 2014 Purdue University
Functional Abstractions for Practical and Scalable Concurrent Programmin Invited Lecture	ng Mar 2014 Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK
Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony PADL 2014	Jan 2014 San Diego, CA
Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud ML Workshop 2013	Sep 2013 Boston, MA
A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC MARC 2012	Nov 2012 RWTH Aachen
Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness ISMM 2012, Beijing Wrestling Wednesdays, Microsoft Research, Cambridge	Jun 2012 May 2012
Lightweight Concurrency in GHC Wrestling Wednesdays	May 2012 Microsoft Research, Cambridge
Efficient Session Type guided Distributed Interaction COORDINATION 2012	Jun 2012 CWI Amsterdam

Professional Service

- Program Committee member: OCaml Workshop 2016, SPLASH-MARC symposium, 2013.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee member: PLDI 2015, PPoPP/CGO 2016.
- Reviewer: TODS, JFP, POPL, ICFP, ASPLOS, TLDI, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, Software: Practice and Experience.

Awards and Recognitions

- Research Fellowship, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851, 2015–2018, £102,000.
- Research Fellowship, Darwin College, Cambridge, 2015–2018, £900.
- Maurice H. Halstead Memorial Award for outstanding research in Software Engineering, Purdue University, 2014,
- Best paper award at Many-core Architecture Research Symposium at RWTH-Aachen, 2012, \$1,000.
- Invited paper in Science of Computer Programming, Vol. 78, Iss. 2 (Feb 2013).
- Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) Committer.

- SIGPLAN PAC travel grant for PLDI 2012 and POPL 2014, \$1,500 each.
- NSF travel grant for ICFP 2013, \$2,000.

References

Suresh Jagannathan

Professor Department of Computer Science Purdue University 305 N University St West Lafayette, IN 47906, USA suresh@cs.purdue.edu

Jan Vitek

Professor of Computer Science College of Computer & Information Science Northeastern University 440 Huntinton Av Boston, MA 02115, USA j.vitek@neu.edu

Anil Madhavapeddy

University Lecturer Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge 15 JJ Thomson Av Cambridge, CB3 0FD, UK anil.madhavapeddy@cl.cam.ac.uk

Simon Peyton Jones

Principal Researcher
Programming Principles and Tools
Microsoft Research Ltd
21 Station Rd
Cambridge CB1 2FB, UK
simonpj@microsoft.com